We looked at machine learning and said that it was a way to
機械学習について見てきました
derive repeated predictive insights from data.
データから繰り返し予測的な情報を 得る方法です
Then, we talked about the two stages of ML, a training phase,
そして MLの2つの段階についても触れました
where you teach the algorithm using labeled examples,
ラベル付きサンプルを使って アルゴリズムをトレーニングする段階
and a prediction or inference stage,
そして予測あるいは推定の段階では
where you use a trained model to make inferences and new data.
トレーニングされたモデルで 推定や新しいデータを生成します
We then looked at a few examples of machine learning in action,
次に 機械学習の実装例を紹介しました
photos, translate, Smart Reply,
Googleフォト、翻訳 スマートリプライなどの
all from Google products.
Googleのサービスです
So, how do you get to the point where
では どうすればあなたの会社でも
your company is innovating like this in machine learning?
機械学習を利用して革新を起こせるでしょうか
Our execs had a unique answer to the question
Googleの経営陣に聞いてみました
of what kinds of problems can machine learning solve.
機械学習で解決できる問題とは何でしょうか
This is Eric Schmidt, the Executive Chairman of the board at Google.
Google会長のEric Schmidtは
He's talking about the new transformation going on at Google,
Googleで行われている変革について触れ
where we're becoming an AI-first company.
AIを優先する企業へと変わりつつあると言います
"Machine learning," says Eric,
Ericの言葉ですが
"This is the next transformation.
「機械学習は次に訪れる変化です
The programming paradigm is changing.
プログラミングのパラダイムは変化しています
It's not programming a computer.
コンピュータをプログラミングするのではなく
You teach a computer to learn something and then it does what you want."
コンピュータに学習方法を教えて 必要なことをさせるのです」
Now, this seems strange.
不思議に思いますか
When you say ML to most people,
MLと聞くと大抵の人は
they think predictions from data,
データからの予測だと思います
but notice that there's nothing in Eric's quote about data.
しかしEricの言葉に「データ」はありません
He's talking about machine learning as a way to replace programming.
機械学習がプログラミングの 代わりになると言っているのです
ML, according to Eric,
EricによるとMLは
is about logic, not just about data. What does he mean?
データのみならず論理なのです どういう意味でしょうか
Consider search. This is,
検索について考えましょう
of course, our flagship application here at Google.
Googleの有名なアプリですね
If you're typing "Giants",
「ジャイアンツ」と入力するとします
should we show you the San Francisco Giants or the New York Giants? How would you do it?
サンフランシスコまたはニューヨーク どちらのジャイアンツを返せばよいでしょうか
A few years ago, this is how Google search worked.
数年前のGoogle検索では 次のように決めていました
There were a bunch of rules that are part of
検索エンジンの コードベースにある複数のルールが
the search engine code base to decide which sports team to show a user.
どちらのチームを表示するか決めます
If they're query is giants,
「ジャイアンツ」と入力したユーザーが 西海岸にいるなら
show them results about San Francisco Giants.
サンフランシスコジャイアンツに関する結果を
If the user is in the New York area,
ユーザーがニューヨーク近辺にいるなら
show them results about New York Giants.
ニューヨークジャイアンツに関する 結果を表示します
If they're anywhere else,
他の地域にいるなら
show them results about tall people,
背の高い人に関する結果を表示します
and this is just for one query.
これは検索の一例にすぎません
Multiply this by the large varieties of queries that people make,
多くの人が さまざまな検索語句で このような検索をしています
and you can imagine how complex the whole code base have become.
コードベースがどれほど複雑になるか 想像できますね
The code base is getting unwieldy because handwritten code,
手作業で書かれたコードやルールの メンテナンスは非常に困難なため
hand-coded rules are really hard to maintain.
コードベースは扱いにくくなっています
So, why not to try machine learning?
そこで機械学習の出番です
Machine learning scales better because it's automated.
機械学習は自動なので スケーリングに優れています
We knew when we showed people results which of the links they actually clicked on.
ユーザーが検索結果のどのリンクを クリックしたかという情報があるので
So, how about training a machine learning model so that it could do the search ranking?
機械学習モデルをトレーニングして検索 ランキングを作成可能にするのはどうでしょう
That was the essential idea behind RankBrain,
それがRankBrainの基本概念でした
a deep neural network for search ranking.
検索ランキングの ディープニューラルネットワークです
It outperformed many human built signals.
人間が作ったシグナルよりも 優れており
We could replace many of the hand-coded rules with machine learning.
多くの手書きコードやルールを 機械学習で置き換えられるようになりました
And the neural network ended up improving our search quality dramatically,
ニューラルネットワークは 検索結果の質を劇的に向上させました
plus the system could continually improve itself based on what users actually preferred.
さらにシステムは ユーザーの実際の 好みに基づいて改善を続けます
Replacing heuristic rules by ML,
MLはヒューリスティックルールに 取って代わります
that's what ML is about.
それがMLの本質です
So, what kinds of problems can you solve with ML?
では MLでどんな問題を解決できるでしょう？
Answer, anything for which you are writing rules today.
答えは 現在あなたがルールを作成している すべての問題です
It's not just about predictive analytics.
予測分析だけではありません
Google Search is not a predictive analytics application,
Google検索は予測分析アプリではありませんが
but we use machine learning for it.
機械学習を実装しています
Notice that saying that machine learning is a way to replace rules,
機械学習はルールに 代わるものだと言いましたが
notice that this is
これは 機械学習でどんな問題が 解決できるか ということより
So, that's what we mean when we say Google is an AI-first company.
GoogleがAI優先の企業であるとは こういう意味なのです
We think of machine learning as a way to scale,
Googleでは 機械学習を
to automate, to personalize.
スケーリングし自動化しパーソナライズする 手段と考えています
Think about all the heuristic rules you're coding up today.
今コードを書いている ヒューリスティックルールを考えてください
Provided you can collect the right data,
適切なデータを入手できるなら
you may be able to do it using machine learning.
機械学習を使って解決できるでしょう
The way you think about problems changes when you do this,
問題に対する見方が変わるはずです
you don't think about coding up rules,
ルールをコード化するのではなく
you think about training models based on data.
データに基づきモデルを訓練するのです
You don't think about fixing bug reports by adding your rules.
ルールを追加してバグを修正する代わりに
You think in terms of continuously training the model as you get new data.
新しいデータで モデルを継続的に訓練します
And instead of thinking about applying specific rules to specific inputs,
特定の入力に対して特定のルールを 適用する代わりに
you instead think in terms of deploying models at scale so that you can make predictions.
モデルを大規模にデプロイして 予測を立てるのです